{
  "q1": [
        {
      "question": "The men's section of this event was dominated by Bill Rodgers in the 1970s. In 1980, Rosie\nRuiz was disqualified from this event after initially \"winning\" its women's title by taking\nshortcuts. From 2002 to 2013, all men's winners of this event were from either Kenya or\nEthiopia. For 10 points, name this distance running event which, in 2013, was attacked by\nterrorists.",
      "answer": [
        "Boston Marathon",
        "New York Marathon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's fictitious sister Judith is hypothesized to make a point about women writers in\nVirginia Woolf's A Room of One's Own. This man left only his \"second-best bed\" to his widow\nAnne Hathaway, but did leave women such roles as Cordelia, Beatrice, and Ophelia. For 10\npoints, name this author of King Lear, Much Ado About Nothing, and Hamlet.",
      "answer": [
        "William Shakespeare",
        "Shakespeare"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Schoolgirl Venetia Burney proposed what is now the official name of this object. This body\nwas discovered in 1930 using the blink comparator machine by Vesto Slipher's new apprentice,\nClyde Tombaugh. In 2006, this object was demoted by the International Astronomical Union to\n\"dwarf planet\" status. For 10 points, name this trans-Neptunian object and former ninth planet.",
      "answer": "Pluto"
    },
    {
      "question": "Peter Shann Ford has attempted to prove, using acoustic analysis, that this man did not flub a\nline that had been scripted for him. This man indicated that \"the Eagle has landed\" while on a\nmission with Michael Collins and Buzz Aldrin. For 10 points, name this commander of Apollo\n11 who said \"one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind\" as he took the first step onto\nthe Moon.",
      "answer": [
        "Neil Armstrong",
        "Armstrong"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to this religion, a compass-like device called the Liahona (pr. LEE-uh-HOH-nuh)\nwas used to show an escape route from Jerusalem. Other artifacts of this religion include Urim\nand Thummim, the \"seer stones\" used to translate the golden plates which the angel Moroni\nrevealed to its founder. For 10 points, name this church founded by Joseph Smith.",
      "answer": [
        "Mormon church",
        "LDS",
        "Latter-Day Saints"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city once turned away foreign help during an earthquake in fear of contaminating its\nsocial system, which involved events such as the \"krypteia\" (pr. crip-TAY-uh), a ritual\ndeclaration of war on its slave class, the helots (pr. HELL-ots). For 10 points, name this city\nwhere two lines of kings oversaw the cultivation of boys from age seven into full-time soldiers.",
      "answer": "Sparta"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Council of Trent mandated that Catholic realms adopt this standard, which did not arrive\nin Greece until 1923. It replaced an earlier standard named for Julius Caesar. When it was\nintroduced to Great Britain in 1751, monthly debtors cried \"give us back our eleven days.\" For\n10 points, identify this modern calendar named for the Pope who devised it.",
      "answer": [
        "Gregorian calendar",
        "Gregorian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "American \"shows\" described by this word featured stock characters such as Mr. Bones and\nperformers dressed in blackface. In the middle ages, this word generally described people such as\nminnesingers (pr. MIN-eh-singers) and troubadours, who sang or played the harp, flute, or lute.\nFor 10 points, name these people who were travelling musicians of the middle ages.",
      "answer": [
        "minstrels",
        "minstrel"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Southern supporters of this man launched racist attacks on his opponent by claiming that this\nman's rival danced with Mary Booze. This man became president of the firm constructing the\nEmpire State Building after losing the 1928 Presidential election to Herbert Hoover. For 10\npoints, name this \"Happy Warrior,\" the first major-party Catholic candidate.",
      "answer": [
        "Al Smith",
        "Smith"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person was appointed as the head of an expedition to Scutari (pr. scoo-TAH-ree) by\nwar minister Sidney Herbert, who knew of her efforts to improve sanitation. She became known\nas the \"Lady with the Lamp\" for her efforts during the Crimean War. For 10 points, name this\n1850s British woman, the founder of modern nursing.",
      "answer": [
        "Florence Nightingale",
        "Nightingale"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(EXAMPLE BONUS QUESTION) Japan underwent an internal political crisis over invading Korea in the Seikanron, a\ncomponent of what larger movement to modernize Japan and replace the Tokugawa shogunate\nwith a constitutional monarchy?",
      "answer": "the Meiji Restoration"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shortly after his death, this man was nominated for an Oscar for his work on Shall We Dance,\nfor which he wrote the song \"They Can't Take That Away From Me\" with his brother Ira. This\ncomposer used traffic horns in the score to An American in Paris and rumbas in his Cuban\nOverture. For 10 points, name this composer of the jazz concerto Rhapsody in Blue.",
        "answer": [
          "George Gershwin",
          "Gershwin"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gershwin adapted a play by DuBose Heyward into what opera, which has been both\npraised and criticized for its portrayal of black South Carolinians on Catfish Row?",
        "answer": "Porgy and Bess"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Bally and Williams corporations grew by manufacturing units for this game. Montague\nRedgrave patented the spring launcher central to this game in 1871, and in 1950, David Gottlieb\ncreated its modern form by adjusting the position of the controllable flippers. For 10 points,\nidentify this arcade game, in which points are scored for keeping the metal balls in play.",
        "answer": "pinball"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What band, which described a \"deaf, dumb, and blind\" \"Pinball Wizard\" in their rock\nopera Tommy, also recorded \"My Generation\" and \"Baba O'Reilly?\"",
        "answer": "The Who"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this African country, the Orange Democratic Movement arose following political\nfragmentation when Daniel arap Moi retired. This country's independence came shortly after\nGeneral China led the Mau Mau Rebellion against British rule here. For 10 points, name this\ncountry where the Leakey family's research on human origins took place at Olduvai Gorge.",
        "answer": "Republic of Kenya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What author of Facing Mount Kenya became Kenya's first prime minister upon\nindependence and is the father of the current Kenyan president?",
        "answer": [
          "Jomo Kenyatta",
          "Kenyatta"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This party effectively ceased to function after the failure of Rufus King's Presidential\ncampaign. They were discredited when members were accused of using blue lights to signal to\nBritish ships during the War of 1812, and by their organization of the secessionist Hartford\nConvention. For 10 points, name this party of DeWitt Clinton, Alexander Hamilton, and John\nAdams.",
        "answer": [
          "Federalist Party",
          "Federalist",
          "Federalists"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What name is given to the period of political unity under James Monroe, in which\nnearly no opposition to the Democratic-Republican Party existed?",
        "answer": "Era of Good Feelings"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Popes from this family presided over the Council of Trent and the start of the Protestant\nReformation. This family of Leo X and Pius IV was targeted by the Pazzi (pr. POT-see)\nConspiracy and first rose to power in Tuscany under the banker Cosimo. For 10 points, identify\nthis political family which ruled Florence through such members as Lorenzo the Magnificent.",
        "answer": [
          "de Medici",
          "Medici"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What rival family of Spanish origin included Pope Alexander VI, the poisoner\nLucrezia, and the Machiavelli (pr. MOCK-ee-uh-VEL-ee) patron Cesare (pr. CHAY-zar-ay)?",
        "answer": "Borgias"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man discussed the fall of the First Republic in his \"Cartagena (pr. cart-uh-HAY-nuh)\nManifesto.\" This man conquered New Granada with his lieutenant, Francisco Santander, and\naccepted a Spanish surrender at Boyacá (pr. boy-uh-CAH). For 10 points, name this \"libertador\"\nwho was the icon of South American independence in Colombia and Venezuela.",
        "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bolívar had a mysterious summit at Guayaquil with what Argentine general, who\nliberated Argentina, Peru, and Chile working in tandem with Bernardo O'Higgins?",
        "answer": "Jose de San Martin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city built the luxurious Segovia Bridge over the unimpressive Manzanares (pr. mon-zuhNAH-race) River. This home of the Queen Sofia Museum became capital in 1560, replacing\nToledo. The palace El Escorial (pr. ess-core-ee-AHL) is found just outside this city, which is the\nhome of the Prado art museum. For 10 points, name this capital of Spain.",
        "answer": "Madrid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Las Ventas site in Madrid is used for what activity, the subject of Ernest\nHemingway's Death in the Afternoon?",
        "answer": [
          "bullfighting",
          "bullfight"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The informer \"Stakeknife\" infiltrated this organization, which began the \"Long War\" in the\nearly 1970s. This group claimed responsibility for killing MP Airey Neave as well as the 1984\nBrighton hotel bombing which nearly killed Margaret Thatcher. For 10 points, name this militant\nCatholic group which advocated transferring Northern Ireland away from the United Kingdom.",
        "answer": [
          "IRA",
          "Irish Republican Army",
          "Provisional IRA",
          "Provisional Irish Republican Army"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which 1972 massacre of Irish demonstrators by UK paratroopers shares its name with\na 1905 killing spree in St. Petersburg?",
        "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "CLEOPATRA",
      "prompt": "Cleopatra VII was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The last Macedonian pharaoh of what land prior to its conquest by Rome?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The mother of a child whose father was what Ides of March assassination victim?",
          "answer": [
            "Julius Caesar",
            "Caesar",
            "Gaius Julius Caesar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Later the partner of what Second Triumvirate member who fought with Octavian?",
          "answer": [
            "Mark Antony",
            "Marcus Antonius",
            "Antony",
            "Antonius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The daughter, sister, and mother of men with what dynastic name?",
          "answer": "Ptolemy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The loser of what 31 BC naval battle which sealed her fate?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Actium",
            "Actium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Killed, in some versions, when she allowed what kind of snake to bite her?",
          "answer": "asp"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presented to her first Roman lover inside what object?",
          "answer": [
            "rolled-up carpet",
            "rug"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Able to fulfill a vow to serve a ten-million-sesterces dinner by serving what item dissolved in\nvinegar?",
          "answer": [
            "pearls",
            "pearl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WORLD WAR I",
      "prompt": "In World War I, who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The country which exited the war following the Bolshevik Revolution and organized the\nUSSR five years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Russia",
            "Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic",
            "Soviet Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The palace outside Paris where the main peace treaty was signed?",
          "answer": "Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "The archduke whose assassination sparked the conflict?",
          "answer": [
            "Franz Ferdinand",
            "Francis Ferdinand"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The assassin responsible for that archduke's death?",
          "answer": [
            "Gavrilo Princip",
            "Princip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The country whose violated neutrality was a proximate cause of Britain’s entering the war?",
          "answer": "Belgium"
        },
        {
          "question": "The high commander of American forces in the war?",
          "answer": [
            "John Pershing",
            "John Joseph Pershing",
            "Black Jack Pershing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The German war plan which involved quickly defeating France before fighting Russia?",
          "answer": [
            "Schlieffen Plan",
            "Schlieffen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The August 1914 battle where Hindenburg and Ludendorff destroyed a Russian army?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Tannenberg",
            "Tannenberg"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MUSSOLINI",
      "prompt": "Benito Mussolini...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the dictator of what country?",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Promoted what ideology named for a Roman bundle of sticks?",
          "answer": "fascism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took on what title meaning \"leader?\"",
          "answer": [
            "Il Duce",
            "Duce"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Authorized the invasion of what African country in 1935, displacing Haile Selassie (hai-LEH\nse-lah-SEE)?",
          "answer": [
            "Ethiopia",
            "Abyssinia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Entered what agreement in May 1939, formally creating the Axis?",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "Stahlpakt",
            "Patto d'Acciaio"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the invasion of what country in 1939, causing the overthrow of King Zog?",
          "answer": "Albania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed trying to flee to which country that borders Italy?",
          "answer": "Switzerland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eventually was hung upside down outside a gas station in which largest Northern Itailan city?",
          "answer": "Milan"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During primaries for this year's election, a candidate won applause in a high school\ngymnasium after yelling \"I am paying for this microphone!\" Another party's primaries in\nthis election year featured a strong challenge to the incumbent from (20 pts) ",
        "Ted Kennedy. This\nelection also included independent candidate John Anderson. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, identify this\nelection year which resulted in the end of Jimmy Carter's Presidency and the start of the Ronald\nReagan administration."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States Presidential election of 1980",
        "1980"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This Supreme Court case was analogous to the Sweatt v. Painter decision which came\ndown four years earlier. The ruling in this Supreme Court case drew on Kenneth and\nMamie Clark's (20 pts) ",
        "doll experiments. A followup to this case ordered its ruling implemented\n\"with all deliberate speed.\" Thurgood (10 pts) ",
        "Marshall successfully argued this case on behalf of\nthe NAACP. For 10 points, name this unanimous 1954 ruling of the Warren court against\nsegregated public schools."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka",
        "Kansas",
        "Brown"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Kicking Bear adapted a Mormon belief into an auxiliary practice of this movement, in\nwhich bullet-repelling shirts were worn. This movement's main ritual was adapted from\nearlier \"circle\" performances by (20 pts) ",
        "Wodziwob, and it spread across the Plains under the\nleadership of (10 pts) ",
        "Wovoka, who preached that it would end white encroachment on Indian lands.\nFor 10 points, name this Indian religious movement whose practitioners were massacred in 1890\nat Wounded Knee."
      ],
      "answer": "Ghost Dance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To show that the Federal Reserve's contractionary economic policy exacerbated the\nGreat Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on A (20 pts) ",
        "y exacerbated the\nGreat Depression, this man collaborated with Anna Schwartz on A (+) Monetary History of\nthe United States. He popularized his ideas on the relationship between the free market and\nindividual liberty in the PBS miniseries Free to Choose. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this leader of\nthe Chicago school of economics who founded monetarism."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Milton Friedman",
        "Friedman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man became President by defeating former Civil War general Benjamin Butler of\nthe Greenback Party and Prohibition candidate John St. John. He edged out his majorparty opponent with a last-minute swing of the (20 pts) ",
        "New York vote, triggered by Samuel\nBurchard denouncing him as the candidate of (10 pts) ",
        "\"rum, Romanism, and rebellion.\" For 10\npoints, name this first post-Civil War Democrat to win the Presidency, who served\nnonconsecutive terms."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Grover Cleveland",
        "Cleveland",
        "Stephen Grover Cleveland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization had a major political effect in 1996, after its weapons master Yahya\nAyyash was killed and it launched a wave of bus bombings. This organization designates its\narmed wing the (20 pts) ",
        "Izzedine al-Qassam (pr. EYE zuh-DEEN ah-kah-SEM) Brigades, and it\ngained popularity by resisting the (10 pts) ",
        "Oslo Accords. For 10 points, name this Islamist group\nwhich opposes the existence of Israel and controls the Gaza Strip."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hamas",
        "Harakat Al-Muqawama Al-Islamia",
        "Islamic Resistance Movement"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Julius von Sachs identified the organelles in which this process takes place. The\nexperiments of Jan Ingenhousz (pr. ING-en-hoos) showed that this process altered the mass\nof the (20 pts) ",
        "organisms involved. Joseph Priestley performed an experiment involving a candle\nand (10 pts) ",
        "mint that showed that this process changes the composition of air. For 10 points, identify\nthis process of plants using light to create sugars from carbon dioxide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "photosynthesis",
        "Calvin cycle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This emperor was the ultimate victor of the Battle of Muhlberg, which suppressed the\nSchmalkaldic (pr. shmal-CALL-dik) League that opposed him. This man's 1525 victory at (20 pts) ",
        "Pavia included the capture of Francis I of France. This father of Philip II summoned (10 pts) ",
        "Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms (pr. VURMZ). For 10 points, name this Hapsburg who\nbriefly united the thrones of Spain and the Holy Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles V",
        "Charles I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) These people were sought out due to the new doctrine of \"limpieza de sangre\" (pr. leempee-EY-zuh day SAHN-gray), or \"cleanliness of blood.\" These people were given a\nderogatory nickname meaning (20 pts) ",
        "\"pig\" and were subject to the public \"auto de fe\" (pr.\nOW-toe deh FAY) if found. Tomas de Torquemada gave these people three months to leave (10 pts) ",
        "Spain in 1492. For 10 points, name these people whom the Inquisition sought to find\nsurvivals of within the \"conversos\" community."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish former Jews",
        "Jew",
        "Jews",
        "secret Jews"
      ]
    }
  ]
}